<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>The funerall pompe and obsequies of the most mighty and puissant Henry the fourth, King of France and Nauarre solemnized at Paris, and at S. Dennis, the 29. and 30 daies of Iune last past. 1610. Together with the order and ceremonie of remouing the body of Henry, the third of that name, King of France and Polonia, at Saint Dennis the 22 of Iune last past. All faithfully translated out of the French coppy printed at Roan by Petit ...</title>
            <title>Pompe funèbre du grand Henry, roy de France et de Navarre. English</title>
            <author>Morillon, Claude, fl. 1600-1615.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1610</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 34 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 13 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-12">2011-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A02996</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 13136</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S103962</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99839704</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99839704</idno>
            <idno type="VID">4150</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A02996)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 4150)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 727:14)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>The funerall pompe and obsequies of the most mighty and puissant Henry the fourth, King of France and Nauarre solemnized at Paris, and at S. Dennis, the 29. and 30 daies of Iune last past. 1610. Together with the order and ceremonie of remouing the body of Henry, the third of that name, King of France and Polonia, at Saint Dennis the 22 of Iune last past. All faithfully translated out of the French coppy printed at Roan by Petit ...</title>
                  <title>Pompe funèbre du grand Henry, roy de France et de Navarre. English</title>
                  <author>Morillon, Claude, fl. 1600-1615.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[28] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed by Nicholas Okes, and are to be sold in Pauls Church-yard [by L. Lisle], at the signe of the Tygers head,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1610.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>A translation of: Morillon, Claude.  Pompe funèbre du grand Henry, roy de France et de Navarre.</note>
                  <note>Bookseller's name from STC.</note>
                  <note>Signatures: A-C⁴ [D]² .</note>
                  <note>The last leaf is blank.</note>
                  <note>Running title reads: The funerall of the French King.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the Henry E. Huntington Library and Art Gallery.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Henry --  IV, --  King of France, 1553-1610 --  Death and burial --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2010-05</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-05</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-07</date>
            <label>Greg Schutz</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-07</date>
            <label>Greg Schutz</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:4150:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:4150:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>THE FVNERALL POMPE AND OB<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>SEQVIES OF THE MOST mighty and puiſſant HENRY the fourth, King of <hi>France</hi> and <hi>Nauarre,</hi> ſolem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nized at <hi>Paris,</hi> and at <hi>S. Dennis,</hi> the 29. and 30 daies of <hi>Iune</hi> laſt paſt. 1610.</p>
            <p>Together with the order and ceremonie of remo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing the body of <hi>Henry,</hi> the third of that name, King of <hi>France</hi> and <hi>Polonia,</hi> at Saint <hi>Dennis the</hi> 22 <hi>of Iune laſt paſt.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>All faithfully tranſlated out of the French Coppy printed at <hi>Roan</hi> by <hi>Petit,</hi> ordinary Stationer, and Printer to the King, by the permiſsion of Superiours.</p>
            <figure>
               <figDesc>fleur-de-lis</figDesc>
            </figure>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON,</hi> Printed by <hi>Nicholas Okes,</hi> and are to be ſold in Pauls Church-yard, at the ſigne of the Tygers head. 1610.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb facs="tcp:4150:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:4150:2"/>
            <head>The funerall pompe celebrated at the buriall of the high and mighty Prince, Henry King of France and Nauar, in the citty of Paris, and the towne of Saint Denis, vpon the 29 and 30 day <hi>of Iune,</hi> 1610.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>He Deſtinies hauing had ſo great power, in ſo golden an age, ſo peaceable a time throughout all Chriſtendome, in a yeare ſo aboundant, and in the middle of the pleaſan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſt moneth thereof, by the hands of a villanous and diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loyal traitour, to bereaue the moſt Chriſtian and flouriſhing kingdome vnder the cope of heauen, of the greateſt King, and moſt accompliſhed Prince for wiſedome, prouidence, magnanimitie, clemen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cie, and mercy, that euer liued in our time, and to ſpeake truth, the mirrour and miracle of Kings, and the King of miracles; as his owne kingdomes, and other foraigne kingdomes and prouinces, yea and thoſe that are faire diſtant, both on this ſide, and beyond the ſeas, beare witneſſe. But leſt I ſhould be ouer tedious, I will not particularly rehearſe the
<pb facs="tcp:4150:3"/>great number of his actions, atchiuements, bat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tailes, and heroicall conqueſts; or the hiſtories ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficiently declare the ſame. I forbeare to ſpeake of his notable and prompt proceedings, and his owne deepe and wiſe counſels. I ceaſſe to ſet downe the wonders of his life, and actions. He was the for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wardeſt of them moſt forward. The firſt in field and the laſt that retired. A louer of the good, and the terrour of the wicked; curious to inrich and beautifie his townes, as his lofty and ſumptu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous buildings may witneſſe vnto all poſterities. But when he thought himſelfe to be ſeated vpon the <hi>Olympus</hi> of his proſperities, repleniſhed with ioy, to haue ſeene his Queene and deare eſpouſe crowned, with as much magnificence, as contentment, which ſhould haue bene augmented at his entry into the famous cittie of <hi>Paris;</hi> after that to mount on horſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>backe, and from thence to goe to place himſelfe at the head and forefront of the puiſſanteſt army that euer <hi>France</hi> ſent into the fields, in mans remem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brance: euen at that time (I ſay) that heauen had bleſſed his ſeed in the multitude of his goodly and princely children left vnto vs, a parricides knife ſuddenly cut off both the execution of his great deſſignes, and the threed of his life; the end whereof hath made mortall men inwardly as much grieued at their hearts, as they ſhewed ſorrow outwardly in their countenances.</p>
            <p>The King being dead, the Queene aſſiſted by the Princes, Prelates, and Officers of the crowne, with determination to yeeld him the laſt duties due vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to
<pb facs="tcp:4150:3"/>him in his obſequies, cauſed order to be taken, not onely that prayer ſhould be made vnto God for his ſoule, but alſo for all things requiſite for the ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>compliſhing of the Funerals of ſo great a Monarch, as you ſhall hereafter particularly reade.</p>
            <p>Two daies after the death of this great King, which was vpon the 16 day of May, his body was laid on a bed, with his face open, that euery man might behold him; and then preparation was made for the ripping and imbalming of his body: from whence they tooke his heart to ſend it to <hi>La Fleſche,</hi> and his bowels to Saint <hi>Denis,</hi> as he had determined in his life time. Which done, he was wrapt in ſeare cloth, and put in a coffin of lead, couered ouer with purple veluet, whereon there was imbroydered a great croſſe of white ſattin.</p>
            <p>The next day after Whitſonday, at 4 a clocke in the morning, the Kings heart was honorably imbal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med, and being put into a little coffin of lead, it was carried to <hi>La Fleſche</hi> (which is the ſepulcher of the King of <hi>Nauarre</hi> his father) by aboue 400 Lords, gentlemen, and others on horſe-backe; the heart be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing borne in a caroach, wherein there ſate 4 Ieſuites to accompany it.</p>
            <div type="part">
               <head>Of the ſtate and manner of the chamber wherein the dead body lay.</head>
               <p>THe body being laid in the coffin, it was ſet in a chamber richly hanged, on the ſides where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of there were diuers altars erected, whereon eue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry
<pb facs="tcp:4150:4"/>day there was a hundred Maſſes high &amp; low ſaid, which were celebrated by ſeueral Prieſts of diuers orders.</p>
               <p>Within the chamber there were diuers benches richly couered, for the Princes, Officers of the crowne, the Lords, Cardinals, Arch-biſhops, Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhops, the Almener, and other Prelates, and officers of the Church, to ſit on; and hard by the Cenſer, there ſtood 2 heraulds of Armes, and diuers ben<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches on both ſides whereon many religious perſons ſate ſinging continually night and day.</p>
               <p>Vpon the Kings body there ſtood the Crowne, Scepter, and hand of Iuſtice, which were placed vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on a cuſhion richly imbroydered.</p>
               <p>The body of the King remained in the ſaid chamber the ſpace of 15 or 16 daies, and then it was carried downe, and borne with great honour, and many ceremonies into the great hall of the Louure, accompanied by diuers Biſhops, Prelates, and great Lords of the Court.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>Of the Hall of honour.</head>
               <p>THe great Hall was hanged with the Kings ri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cheſt and moſt ſumptuous hangings, not onely from the toppe to the bottome, but alſo on the ground. On each ſide of the ſaid hall there were two galleries, on either ſide one, for the Princes and great Lords to paſſe through; which galleries were all richly hanged.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <pb facs="tcp:4150:4"/>
               <head>Of the Bed of Honour, and the Kings Image.</head>
               <p>AT the vpper end of the hall there was a tribu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nall place made foure ſteppes high, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on was placed a great pallet bed, couered with cloath of gold; and on it lay the Kings image, made of waxe, with his hands cloſe together, appa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>relled in his royall robes, and the crowne vpon his head, which reſted vpon a cuſhion richly imbroide<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red. Vpon his royall cloake he had thecollar of the Order; on his right ſide his Scepter royall, on his left the hand of Iuſtice.</p>
               <p>Hard by the image there were two altars ere<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cted ſumptuouſly ſet forth; the one on the right, the other on the left ſide; vpon that on the right ſide, there was a Maſſe of <hi>Requiem</hi> with muſicke, ſaid; and on that on the left ſide, foure other high Maſſes; ouer each altar there hung a rich cano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pie, and betweene thoſe altars there were diuers ſeates for Prelates and religious perſons, that ſong continually, as they did in the chamber: and all a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>long in the neather part of the hall there were diuers other altars placed, which alſo were richly ſet forth, whereon there were diuers low Maſſes ce<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lebrated.</p>
               <p>The image being placed in this manner hard by his body, in the hall, euery day ordinarily there was meate ſerued vpon the table by the officers of the houſe, Buttlers, Caruers, Sewers, Taſters, Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moners, and others; and ſuch order vſed and ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerued as if the King had bene liuing, both for ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſting,
<pb facs="tcp:4150:5"/>bleſſing, and giuing thankes: which done, the meate was giuen vnto the poore.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>Of the Hall hanged all with blacke.</head>
               <p>THe 2<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> day of <hi>Iune</hi> the Kings image and all the tapeſtrie hangings were taken and carryed a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>way, and all the hall was hung from the top to the bottome, and alſo vnder foot, with blacke cloath: and then the body of the King lying in his coffin, was layd in the place of his image, couered ouer with blacke veluet which hung downe to the ground, with a croſſe of white ſattin, and a cano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pie ouer it of blacke veluet.</p>
               <p>Vpon the Kings coffin ſtood the royall crowne, the collar of the Order, the Scepter royall, and the hand of Iuſtice. At the foot of the coffin there was a croſſe of ſiluer, which lay vpon a cuſhion; and hard by it great waxe candles continually burning in candleſtickes of ſiluer; and there alſo ſtood the Cenſer of ſiluer, and on each ſide of his corps two heralds of Armes, who euery two howres were re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leeued by two others which came in their places. The 22 day of <hi>Iune Henry</hi> the third, king of <hi>France</hi> and <hi>Polonia,</hi> was borne to S. <hi>Dennis,</hi> conducted by the Duke <hi>d'Eſpernon,</hi> accompanied by a great num<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber of Lords and officers of the ſaid King; and the next day his funerals were celebrated by the Car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinall <hi>de Ioyeuſe,</hi> Archbiſhop of Roan: and after that his body was buried in the vault by his father <hi>Henry</hi> the ſecond, the Queene his mother, and the Lords his brethren deceſſed.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <pb facs="tcp:4150:5"/>
               <head>The order obſerued by the King in caſting of holy water vpon the body of his dead father.</head>
               <p>THe 25 day of <hi>Iune Lewis</hi> the 13. of that name, King of <hi>France</hi> and <hi>Nauarre,</hi> at this preſent reigning, dined at the houſe of <hi>Longueuille,</hi> and af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter dinner he was led with great magnificence vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the <hi>Louure,</hi> to caſt holy water vpon the body of his father the dead King; and with him his two brethren were borne on each ſide of him, the one Duke of <hi>Orleans</hi> on the right hand, and the other Duke of <hi>Auiou</hi> on the left: hard by his maieſty went the Cardinals <hi>de Ioyeuſe</hi> and <hi>Surdy.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>The King mourned in a princely roabe of Vio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>let with a long traine, which was borne vp by the Princes of <hi>Conty, de Soyſſons, de Guiſe, de Iainuille,</hi> and <hi>de'Elleboeuf,</hi> followed by the Marſhals of <hi>France,</hi> and the Knights of the Order.</p>
               <p>Many Biſhops, Prelates, great Lords, and an infi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nite number of noble men, great Ladyes, and gen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tlewomen attending in the hall for the Kings com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ming: who hauing caſt the holy water vpon his fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers body, went from the <hi>Louure</hi> againe.</p>
               <p>The next day the officers of the Court of Parli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ament at their comming out of the court at ten of the clocke in the morning, went alſo in their accu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtomed order to the <hi>Louure</hi> to caſt holy water, fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowed by the officers of the chamber of accompts, and aids, the Kings receiuers, the officers of iuſtice, the prouoſt of <hi>Paris,</hi> the prouoſt of Merchants, and the Shriefes of the citie</p>
               <pb facs="tcp:4150:6"/>
               <p>On Munday the 28 of <hi>Iune</hi> the twelue ſworne cryers of <hi>Paris,</hi> by commandement giuen vnto them, with the Kings armes hanging both before at their breaſts, and backes, went throughout the city of <hi>Paris</hi> ringing their belles, to ſignifie the celebra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of the Kings funerall, pronouncing with a lowd voice theſe words following.</p>
               <p>All noble and deuout perſons, pray for the ſoule of the moſt high, moſt puiſſant, and moſt excellent Prince, <hi>Henry</hi> the great, by the grace of God King of <hi>France</hi> and <hi>Nauarre,</hi> moſt Chriſtian, moſt imperiall, and moſt victorious, incomparable for magnanimity and clemencie, who is dead in his pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lace <hi>de Louure;</hi> pray vnto God that he may receiue his ſoule.</p>
               <p>On tueſday at two of the clocke after noone, his Maieſties body ſhall bee brought to the Church in <hi>Paris,</hi> in which place the ſame day ſhall be ſaid both euening prayer and the Vigiles for the dead, and the next day in the morning his Seruices and accuſtomed prayers; which done, his body ſhall be borne to the Church of Saint <hi>Denis,</hi> the ſepulchre of the Kings of <hi>France,</hi> and there buri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed; pray for his ſoule.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>The manner of carying the Kings body to our Lady Church in Paris.</head>
               <p>TVeſday the 28 day of <hi>Iune</hi> the ſtreetes were all hanged with blacke on both ſides the way, from the <hi>Louure</hi> to our Ladyes Church, whereon
<pb facs="tcp:4150:6"/>were placed the armes of the King, and the armes of the citie, one hard by the other, and at euery houſe a burning torch.</p>
               <p>The ſame day 2 howres after noone the funerall began to ſet forth in order, as hereafter followeth.</p>
               <p>Firſt marched the Captaines, Lieutenants, and enſigne-bearers of the towne-houſe with their long gownes, their ſwords by their ſides, and in their hoods and cornets; the archers and croſſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bowes of the ſaid towne following them in colou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red caſſockes, imbroidered with black hoods ouer them to the number of 172, marching two and two with their matches lighted, and their halbards and peeces with the poynts and noſes downe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards vnder their armes, which were diuided into three ranckes.</p>
               <p>After them went the Spiritualty in order as fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loweth.</p>
               <p>Firſt the penitentiall fathers of the third order of S. <hi>Francis,</hi> to the number of threeſcore.</p>
               <p>The fathers of the third order of S. <hi>Lewes,</hi> to the number of 45.</p>
               <p>The Capettes, otherwiſe called the poore ſchol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lers of the Colledge of <hi>Mountagne,</hi> to the number of 33.</p>
               <p>The <hi>Capuchines</hi> to the number of 83.</p>
               <p>The <hi>Minimes</hi> to the number of 68.</p>
               <p>The <hi>Cordeliers</hi> to the number of 224, grey Fryars.</p>
               <p>The <hi>Iacobins</hi> to the number of 190.</p>
               <p>The <hi>Augustins</hi> to the number of 100.</p>
               <p>The <hi>Carmelites</hi> to the number of 50.</p>
               <pb facs="tcp:4150:7"/>
               <p>The<note n="*" place="margin">Of which Order <hi>Francis R<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1+ letters">
                           <desc>•…</desc>
                        </gap>
                        <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uiliack</hi> was one.</note> 
                  <hi>Fueillans</hi> to the number of 35.</p>
               <p>Before all thoſe religious Orders, their croſſes were borne, &amp; on the ſides of each croſſe 4 torches, on each ſide of which torches were placed the Scutchions and armes of the ſaid King; after them went 500 poore men in long blacke gownes, with hoodes, hoſe, in manner and forme, and ſhooes in like ſort, each of them carying a burning torch in their hands, whereon hung the double armes of the King.</p>
               <p>Next them followed the 24 ſworne cryers of the citty of <hi>Paris</hi> ringing their bels, with the Kings armes at their breaſts and backes.</p>
               <p>After them the knight of the watch with his lieutenant in black, with a ſtaffe in his hand, follow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed by all his company, in their caſſocks, with cornets of blacke cloth at their backs. In the middle of the company went the enſigne bearer, drawing his en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſigne vpon the ground, all couered ouer with blacke fipres, the drums founding in dolefull manner, all couered with blacke.</p>
               <p>After them went the Sergeants of the Chate<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>let in long blacke gownes, and cornered caps, each with a blacke ſtaffe in his hand to the number of 30.</p>
               <p>After went the Sergeants of the towne houſe on the left hand, and the Sergeants of the Chatelet on horſe-backe on the right hand.</p>
               <p>Next them followed the Notaries, Commiſſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries of quarters, Atturnies, and Aduocates of the Chatelet, all in order, apparelled in long blacke gownes, and cornered capes, on the right ſide; and
<pb facs="tcp:4150:7"/>the Atturneis, Commiſſaries, Clearkes, and citti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zens of the towne on the left hand, all apparelled in the ſame manner.</p>
               <p>After followed the lieutenant ciuill of the Cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>telet on the right hand, and the lieutenant Crimi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nall on the left hand, followed by the Counſellours of the Chaletet.</p>
               <p>Then followed the religious perſons of S. <hi>Auoy, alias Piquet.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>The white Cloakes.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>S. Catherines</hi> in the valley.</p>
               <p>The Colledge of <hi>Mathurins.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>S. Paul.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>S. Steuens</hi> of the mount, with two other Pariſhes.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>S. Euſtache, S. Croix</hi> of the citty, <hi>S. Sauueur, S. Iacques</hi> of the ſhambels, with two other Pariſhes: 4. other Pariſhes, <hi>S. Geruais, S. Protex, S. Innocent, S. Germaine</hi> the old, with an other Pariſh.</p>
               <p>S. <hi>Hillary, S. Iames</hi> of the hoſpitall.</p>
               <p>S. <hi>Martial, S. Steues de</hi> Grey.</p>
               <p>S. <hi>Nicolas de chardonneret.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>S. <hi>Barthelmew,</hi> S. <hi>Seuerin.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>La Magdaleine,</hi> S. <hi>Suplex.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>The <hi>Bernardins,</hi> S. <hi>Magloire,</hi> or S. <hi>Iacques du haut pas,</hi> S. <hi>Martin</hi> in the fields, and on the right hand S. <hi>Germain de Prez.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>S. <hi>Vistor,</hi> S. <hi>Geneuiefue:</hi> The 4 little ſonnes of our Lady, <hi>viz.</hi> S. <hi>Bennet,</hi> S. <hi>Merry,</hi> S. <hi>Oportune,</hi> and S. <hi>German de Lannerrois.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>S. <hi>Honore,</hi> S. <hi>Thomas,</hi> and S. <hi>Nicholas du Louure,</hi> our Lady with the holy Chappell, and S. <hi>Marcel</hi> ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ging;
<pb facs="tcp:4150:8"/>and on the left hand went the Vniuerſity: <hi>viz.</hi> the Maſters of Arte, Licenciates, Principals, Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gents, Batchelers, Doctors of phyſicke, in red robes and miters: Doctors of the Canon &amp; Ciuill lawes, Doctors of Diuinity of all Orders, the Beadles of the Vniuerſitie, and the Rector.</p>
               <p>After them went the ſworne meſſengers, &amp; next the maiſter Porters of the gates, with long blacke gownes, and hoods.</p>
               <p>Then followed the pages of the querie, apparel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led in blacke ſearge.</p>
               <p>Then followed the maiſters of the ho-boyes, flutes, inſtruments of muſicke, trumpets, and drums, all couered, with blacke, ſounding mourne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fully.</p>
               <p>After them went Mounſieur <hi>de Cryquy,</hi> on the right ſide, and Mounſieur <hi>de Lecure,</hi> on the left hand, followed by the Captaines, lieutenants, and enſigne bearers of the Kings guard and regi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments.</p>
               <p>Mounſieur the chiefe Prouoſt of the houſe fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowing after them on horſeback, apparelled in black with a long traine borne vp by his Officers, follow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed by his lieutenants, enſignes, and archers on foot, with long blacke gownes and hoods, and their caſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſockes vpon them, carrying their halbards and pee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces vnder their armes.</p>
               <p>Then the Captaine of the gates of the Kings houſe with his Porters, in their imbroydered caſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſockes, with blacke hoods vpon them.</p>
               <pb facs="tcp:4150:8"/>
               <p>Mounſieur <hi>Marolles</hi> went on the right hand of Mounſieur <hi>de Bouillon,</hi> and Mounſieur <hi>de la Bordoi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiere</hi> his lieutenant, followed by the Captaines of a hundred <hi>Switſers</hi> of the body, apparelled in blacke cloth, and vnſhorne chamblet, with round bonnets pleated of chamblet, their enſigne couered with blacke ſipres.</p>
               <p>Mounſieur <hi>de la Palus</hi> at the head of two com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>panies of 200 gentlemen pentioners, followed by two enſignes, <hi>viz.</hi> that of Mounſieur <hi>le Vidame de Man</hi> on the right hand, and that of Mounſieur <hi>de la Bordoiſiere</hi> on the left hand, all apparelled in blacke ſearge with cornets.</p>
               <p>Then followed the ordinary Officers of the Kings houſe, to the number of 160.</p>
               <p>Next them the Muſitians, Phyſitions, Chirurgi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, yeomen of the wardrobe, and of the Kings chamber, euery one ſeuerally.</p>
               <p>Then the Vſhers of the hall bareheaded, with their hoods hanging downe.</p>
               <p>The Gentlemen ſeruitors, and Maiſters of the houſe on the right hand, the receiuers of the mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ney, ayds, and chamber of accounts, on the left hand.</p>
               <p>Next them went 8. trumpetters in mourning weedes, the trumpets couered all with blacke ſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pres.</p>
               <p>Mounſieur <hi>de Rhodes</hi> maiſter of the ceremonies, caried the Kings penon.</p>
               <p>Then followed the chariot of armes coue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red with a great canopy of blacke veluet, with
<pb facs="tcp:4150:9"/>a croſſe of white ſattin vpon it, in it hauing foure and twentie great ſcutchions of <hi>France</hi> richly im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>broidered, drawne by ſixe great horſes, all couered with blacke veluet downe to the ground, with a croſſe of white fattin through the midſt, led by two watchmen in blacke veluet with their hoods hanging downe.</p>
               <p>Then followed meſſengers <hi>de Vitry</hi> &amp; <hi>de Parlim,</hi> wearing their collars of the Order vpon their long gownes.</p>
               <p>Then went 12 great horſes all couered with black veluet downe to the ground, with croſſes of white ſattin: vpon each of them there fate a page apparel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led in blacke veluet, bare headed, with their hoods veiled.</p>
               <p>The follow Eſquires, <hi>Beniamin</hi> the head E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſquire, bearing gilt ſpurres.</p>
               <p>Next him the eſquire <hi>Betzebe,</hi> bearing the gant<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lets.</p>
               <p>Monſieur <hi>Pluuine</hi> bare the ſcutchion of <hi>France</hi> and <hi>Nauarre,</hi> and another Squire bare the coate of armes.</p>
               <p>The chiefe Squire bare the helmet mantled with a royal mantle of purple veluet <hi>ſeme defluers de lyt,</hi> &amp; lined with ermins, the royal crowne ſtanding vpon the ſaid helmet all couered ouer with blacke ſipres; euery one of the Squiers that bare the ſaid honours being on horſebacke in long blacke gownes, and hoods.</p>
               <p>Then follow the Kings Preachers, Confeſſors, and Almoners.</p>
               <pb facs="tcp:4150:9"/>
               <p>Next them went 17 Archbiſhops and Biſhops on foote, two and two together, all with white Miters on their heads, with capes of blacke vel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uet, and after them went the Archbiſhop of Ly<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons alone, ſomewhat diſtant from all the reſt.</p>
               <p>After him followed the Embaſſadors of <hi>Sauoye, Venice</hi> and <hi>Spaine</hi> on horſebacke, apparrelled in blacke, with long traines, euery one borne vp by ſixe of their officers, each embaſſadour being led by an Archbiſhop, or a Biſhop riding on their mules.</p>
               <p>The Popes two <hi>Nuntioes,</hi> ordinary and extraor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinary, went next them, and on each ſide of them went the Archbiſhop of <hi>Aix</hi> and <hi>Ambrun</hi> mounted on their mules.</p>
               <p>Then followed my Lords the moſtreuerent Car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinals <hi>de Ioyeuſe</hi> and <hi>Surdy,</hi> with their purple capes, and red hats, mounted vpon their mules, &amp; follow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed by their Officers.</p>
               <p>Next followed the horſe of honour, all couered with blue veluet, ſigned with Flower de luces done of gold, as thicke as might be, with a fringe of gold about it, and a ſaddle and ſtirrops richly guilt; there was no part of the horſe ſeene but his eyes: it was led by two Squiers, each holding a reine, and both on foote with their hoods hanging down: on both ſides of the ſaid horſe there went ten heraults of armes, apparelled in blacke, and hoods accordingly with their coate armors, vpon there blacke gownes all imbroydered with Flower de luces of gold.</p>
               <pb facs="tcp:4150:10"/>
               <p>The head Eſquire after them riding vpon a horſe couered with blacke veluet, with a great croſſe of white ſattin, bearing the royall ſword in a ſcarfe, with a ſcabberd of purple veluet imbroydered with Flower de luces of gold.</p>
               <p>Then followed fourteene Vſhers of the court of Parliament, with their little wands in their hands, and after them the Preſidents and Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſellours in ſcarlet roabes, to the number of eighty nine.</p>
               <p>Then followed two Vſhers of the Chamber with their Maces, bare headed with their hoods veiled.</p>
               <p>Alſo went the Biſhop of <hi>Paris,</hi> and the Biſhop of <hi>Angiers</hi> on his left ſide, with their Miters and ſurplices and capes of blacke veluet.</p>
               <p>Then followed the Kings Image in the ſame honour that it lay in the great hall of the Louure, on his right hand holding the Scepter royall, and on his left hand, the hand of Iuſtice, borne by the bearers of the great ſeale of <hi>Paris.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>About the ſaid Image went the foure chiefe Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſidents with diuers Counſellours of the great Chamber, and the Scottiſh Archers of the Kings guard.</p>
               <p>The Canopie ouer it was made of cloth of gold, and the vnder part of it of purple veluet im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>broydered with Flower de luces of gold, and a
<pb facs="tcp:4150:10"/>fringe of gold about it, which was borne by the Prouoſt of Merchants and the Shriefes of the citty of <hi>Paris.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Then followed the Earle of Saint <hi>Paul,</hi> bea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring the ſtaffe of high Steward, repreſenting Mounſieur <hi>de Sciſsons,</hi> high Steward of <hi>France,</hi> on the right hand, and Mounſieur <hi>le Cheuali<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er de Guiſe</hi> repreſenting Mounſieur <hi>le Duc de Eſguillon,</hi> High Chamberlaine, bearing the banner of <hi>France</hi> on the left hand, moun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted vpon two great horſes couered and hoo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded with blacke veluet, with croſſes of white ſattin.</p>
               <p>Then followed Mounſieur the Prince of <hi>Conty</hi> vpon a little horſe, hooded, and in com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plete mourning, wearing vpon the ſame the col<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lar of the Order, his traine being borne vp by ſeuen Gentlemen.</p>
               <p>After him followed Mounſieur <hi>County</hi> of <hi>Soiſſons,</hi> alſo on horſe-backe in the ſame ſort, and in like mourning.</p>
               <p>Then followed Mounſieur <hi>le Duc de Guiſe</hi> without the Order, but in the like mourning habit; after him went the Prince of <hi>Ianuile</hi> on horſe-backe in complete mourning, without the Order.</p>
               <p>Then the Duke <hi>de Ellebæufe</hi> on horſe-backe in the ſame manner of mourning. Then the Duke <hi>de Eſpernon</hi> followed him on horſe-backe, with
<pb facs="tcp:4150:11"/>with the order in like complete, and after him the Duke <hi>de Mountbazon,</hi> in the ſame order and mour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning: their traines were borne vp, by gentlemen their owne followers.</p>
               <p>The Vſher of the order bearing a blacke wand in his hand, apparelled in blacke with his hood downe.</p>
               <p>After the Princes &amp; Dukes followed the knights of the Order on foot, with their colours vpon their mourning gownes, their traines borne vp by their pages.</p>
               <p>Then followed a great number of Noble men, two and two together.</p>
               <p>And after them the twelue pages of the chamber in blacke veluet, with their bonnets.</p>
               <p>And after them followed the captaines of 400. Archers of the guard, with their enſignes, follow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed by the Archers of their ſaid guard, bearing their armes downeward, in blacke gownes and hoods.</p>
               <p>Before their departure from the Louure, there was ſome controuerſy betweene the great perſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nages, the court of Parliment, and Scottiſh guard, but by the Queenes wiſe direction it was well pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cified.</p>
               <p>This was the order which they obſerued in going from the Caſtle of Louure to our Lady Church, going ouer the new bridge, along by the <hi>Augu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtines,</hi> &amp; ſo paſſing ouer S. <hi>Michaels</hi> bridge through the new market, &amp; from thence to the ſaid Church, wherein to they entred at nine of the clocke in the euening.</p>
               <pb facs="tcp:4150:11"/>
               <p>The ſtreets were hanged with black cloth, &amp; vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on the ſame the Kings armes faſtned, with the armes of the citty not farre from it all the way as they went.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>How our Lady Church in <hi>Paris</hi> and the hearſe were adorned.</head>
               <p>THe body of the deceaſſed King was ſet in the middle of the quire of the ſaid Church, vnder the light hearſe, which was erected about a pickes high.</p>
               <p>The quire of the ſaid Church was hanged with blacke cloth, and in the middle thereof there was a range of blacke veluet all along, vpon the which the Scutchions and armes of the King were faſtened, two foote diſtant one from the other.</p>
               <p>The great body of the ſaid Church, was like<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe hanged with the ſame throughout all the ſaid Church, vpon and betweene the ſaid pillars with the other circuit thereof, about in euery place, was full of waxe tapers and lights.</p>
               <p>And the ſame euening there was euening prayer, and vigiles for the dead.</p>
               <p>The next day in the morning being the laſt day of the moneth of Iune, The Princes, Cardinals, Lords, and Officers of the crowne, the court of Parliament, Couents, Pariſhes, &amp; all thoſe that had accompanied the body of the King the day before, came againe to the ſame Church of our Lady
<pb facs="tcp:4150:12"/>about ten of the clocke in the morning, where then Diuine Seruice was celebrated by the Biſhop of <hi>Paris.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>And after the offering, the Biſhop of <hi>Heres,</hi> made the funerall oration, which continued a long houre. All the ſeruices were finiſhed by two of the clocke in the afternoone; and from thence all the Princes, Cardinals, Biſhops, and all the principall perſons went to dinner to the Biſhop, and in other places not farre from thence, where prouiſion was made for them.</p>
               <p>In the meane time the foremoſt of the traine beganne to goe forward each in their firſt order and ranckes, which they had holden the day be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore, from the Louure to our Lady Church, paſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing ouer our Lady bridge, and along through Saint <hi>Denis</hi> ſtreete, till they came to Saint <hi>Denis</hi> in <hi>France,</hi> without any ſtay.</p>
               <p>The ſtreetes from the ſaid Church of our La<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy, to the gates of <hi>Paris</hi> called Saint <hi>Denis</hi> gate, were hanged with blacke cloth on both ſides, and on them the armes of the King, and the armes of the Towne, one an elle diſtant from the other.</p>
               <p>The religious perſons and Prieſtes of the Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſhes, as alſo the Fathers, Confeſſours, Almo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ners, Batchelers, Regents of the Vniuerſity, and Donors of Diuinity, accompanied the body of the King through the towne, euery one in their order vntill they came to the Church of
<pb facs="tcp:4150:12"/>Saint <hi>Ladred,</hi> which is in the ſuburbs of Saint <hi>Dennis;</hi> from which place the greateſt part re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tired, and left the body of the King: which was accompanied by all the Court, with his officers of the Court of Parliament, the Princes, Dukes, Earles, Lords, Gentlemen, Captaines, Guards, Archers, and Prieſts from our Lady Church to the croſſe which ſtandeth in the middle way be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tweene Saint <hi>Dennis</hi> and <hi>Paris;</hi> at the which place the Priour and religious perſons of Saint <hi>Dennis,</hi> came to receiue the body. There the Prieſts of the pariſhes departed, and the Cardi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nals, Biſhops, Princes, Dukes, Earles, Lords, and all the Court, both of the King, and of the Parliament, and the officers, accompanyed the body to Saint <hi>Dennis</hi> Church, where it was ſet vnder a light hearſe, eleuated on high, where certaine Vigiles and Suffrages were ſaid for the dead.</p>
               <p>The ſaid Church of Saint <hi>Dennis</hi> was han<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged with blacke, both in the Quire and the bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy thereof, vpon it hauing a broade range of blacke veluet, which went cleane through the Church, whereon the Kings armes were made faſt.</p>
               <p>The high Maſſe was celebrated by the Car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinall <hi>de Ioyeuſe,</hi> and anſwered with muſicke.</p>
               <p>After the offering, the Biſhop of Angiers made the funerall Oration,</p>
               <pb facs="tcp:4150:13"/>
               <p>This office being performed, and the accuſtomed prayers and oraiſons ſaid, the maiſter of the cere<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monies tooke the Crowne, the Scepter, and the hand of Iuſtice off from the kings corps, which ſtood vpon it, and together with the cloth of gold. Then the Gentlemen pentioners and the archers, bare the body to the graue, which was before the high Altar of the ſaid Church, on the right hand.</p>
               <p>Then the Cardinall <hi>de Ioyueſe</hi> went and caſt earth vpon the body, and the laſt holy water; that done he ſate downe by the graue by the high Altar, and the maiſter of the ceremonies on the other ſide, and betweene them a herault of armes, who calling the Gentlemen one after the other that had borne the Kings honours, which being brought were throwne into the graue.</p>
               <p>That done the Earle of S. <hi>Paul,</hi> ſtruck with his high ſtewards ſtaffe vpon the ground, and with a loud voice ſaid, The king is dead. Then the herault of armes taking the word from him ſaid three times one after the other, The King is dead, the King is dead, the King is dead, all of you pray for his ſoule. Then euery man fell downe on their knees and wept.</p>
               <p>A little while after, the Earle of Saint <hi>Paul</hi> tooke the ſtaffe in his hand againe, and ſaid: God ſaue the King, God ſaue the King, God ſaue the King, <hi>Lewis</hi> the 13 of that name, by the grace of God King of <hi>France</hi> and <hi>Nauarre,</hi> moſt Chriſtian, our
<pb facs="tcp:4150:13"/>foueraigne Lord and good maiſter, to whom God grant moſt happy and long life. Which words en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded, Trumpets, Shackbuts, Flutes, and Phifes began to ſound.</p>
               <p>After that each of the ſaid Lords took vp againe the ſaid peeces of honor, which they had throwne into the graue, and the Princes and great Lords were conducted to the great hall, where the fune<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall feaſt was prepared for dinner.</p>
               <p>Euery man hauing dined, the Officers of the Court of Parliament, of the Chamber of account, of the Aides, of the Receipts, of the Towne houſe, of <hi>Paris,</hi> and other Officers aſſembled together in the hall; where the Earle of <hi>S. Paul</hi> holding the ſtewards ſtaffe in his hand, made a little oration vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to them touching the Kings death, offering them his ſeruice: with promiſe to recommend them vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the King now reigning, to the end that he ſhould continue them in their offices, and eſtates: and to ſhew that he himſelfe alſo was out of office, he brake his ſtaffe in preſence of them all.</p>
            </div>
            <trailer>FJNJS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
